hey guys this looks like a fun one it
has two circles inside of a square and
it wants to know what is this angle this
angle is created with these three points
of tangency if you want to try it on
your own postive right now cuz I'm going
to solve it in 3 2 1 first I want to get
this question mark out of the way and
then we'll construct the common tangent
line of these two circles let's label
this angle X De and this angle y de now
our goal is to find what is x + y next
let's label the centers of both of these
circles this radius will be at right
angles to this side right here and
that's because the tangent line is
always at right angles to the radius
that intersects at that point here's the
theorem right here and then let's
connect this other radius and that'll be
at right angles to this tangent line
let's find the size of this angle right
here we know that y plus this angle has
to equal 90° that means this angle is
the same thing as 90 - y de and let's
look at this triangle more closely this
side and this side are both radi of the
circle since these two sides are equal
that means this is an isoceles triangle
and when you an isoceles triangle these
base angles are also equal so since this
one is 90- y that means this one will
also be 90- Y and now looking up here
since this is 90 minus y and this whole
thing is 90 that leaves y for this angle
right here so we've shown that both of
these angles are equal to Y de and now
let's go back up here and we're going to
do basically the same thing if we
connect this radius it'll be at right
angles to this tangent line and now to
find this angle if this is X that leaves
90- X for this angle and if we complete
complete this radius this makes another
Isles triangle and that's because this
radius is equal to this radius and in
all Isles triangles the base angles are
congruent so if this is 90 - x that
means this one is also 90 - x since this
is 90 - x that leaves X for this angle
right here next let's get rid of this
piece of the tangent line and we're
going to combine the angle X and the
angle y to get X Plus Y and then since
this whole thing is a square that means
this angle right here is a 90° Angle now
we have a really cool looking
quadrilateral the sum of the interior
angles of any quadrilateral is equal to
360° that means if we add up all these
angles we'll get
360° so x + x + y + y + 90 is equal to
360 and then from here we can subtract
90 from both sides of the equation we
end up with x + x + y + y is equal to
270 and then y + y is equal to 2 y and x
+ x is equal to 2x next we can divide
both sides of the equation by two on the
left hand side we have X + y and on the
right hand side 270 / 2 is 135 so now in
the place of this x + y we can plug in
135° and this 135 is in the same place
as the question mark so we know that the
question mark is equal to
135° this is the answer to our question
let's put a box around it how exciting
hey guys it's a couple days later and I
was editing the video and I realized I
missed something that I wanted to share
with you it doesn't matter how big the
circles are the circle can go all the
way up to here till it hits the top or
it can go all the way down here till
this one hits the side the angle will be
135° in all these scenarios and there
was another detail I wanted to share
there's another reason why these two
angles match and these two angles match
if you have a circle and you extend two
tangent lines until they intersect these
two sides will always be congruent so
that means this forms an isoc triangle
and these two base angles would be
congruent so if you isolate this
triangle right here these two sides are
equal making these two base angles equal
or on this other side if you isolate
these in extend them these two sides
would be equal making these base angles
equal I hope you guys like these two
bonus insights how exciting